<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mihai Coșăreanu</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 22:45:46 +0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 22:45:46 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Steve Vai Masterclass</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought I’d write a review about Steve Vai’s masterclass that I’ve attended in Bucharest on June 24, 2013. Probably every masterclass with Steve is different depending on the size of the venue or the number of participants, but I will talk about my personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The venue was Tribute club and there were probably around 50 participants. The ticket for the masterclass was 300 RON and with 100 RON more you could get a ticket for the next day’s show as well. You could also win an Ibanez RG series guitar in a lucky draw at the end of the masterclass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the price might seem high for Romania, the masterclass with Steve is different than other guitar masterclasses you see on the internet. He doesn’t talk about picking technique, finger exercises, arpeggios, or other technical things that you could easily find on the internet. Instead, he touched on subjects such as entering the state of inspiration, developing a musical idea, publishing, finding your own ways to express complex feelings, things that for me seemed to be a great value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention the fact that you could bring your guitar and jam with Steve, a thing that I wished for since I started playing Steve’s songs (although in my dreams it was a live concert, but hey! It’s an opportunity as well, isn’t it?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-it-happened&quot;&gt;How It Happened&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed to show up around 4 o’clock, an hour before the masterclass begun. The rules seemed to be pretty strict, no mobile phones and no cameras, they told us we are going to be searched, although they allowed us to enter with the mobile phones without using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were told to bring our guitars if you wanted to participate at the jam session, so I wrote my name on the case of my guitar and took it with me. Me and my dad found a place to sit, and waited for the event to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve came in, he introduced himself for those who didn’t know him (I doubt that there was anybody who came at the event without knowing what it’s about). He told us “the agenda”: first he is going to talk on some subjects, then we could engage in discussions by asking questions, then the jam session, then the lucky draw and finally the autograph and photo session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;teachings-of-steve&quot;&gt;Teachings of Steve&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a short summary of Steve’s talk: Each of us is capable of doing something better or different than the rest of the world. Our mission is to identify what that thing is, what we enjoy doing, and once we find it we should nurture that passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you do something that you enjoy, you’ll put far more work, dedication and time into developing your passion and you’ll be more successful than doing anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important thing that we should develop, says Steve, is the ability to focus on an action, to try to get rid of all the running thoughts from our mind that make us inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many more specific topics that he covered, but these were the most important ones. He then played one more song for us and then the questions followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked the first question: “How do you get from a musical idea of a couple of seconds to a full-length song?”. He gave us a couple of examples of how to play with the idea and develop it, it is pretty hard to explain in words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t expect superficial questions to come such as “What speakers do you use?” or “Do you have other passions where you put the same dedication as in playing guitar?”. I thought it was a guitar masterclass and the people who came there weren’t interested in Steve the beekeeper, but in Steve the musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from a question regarding his fasting before recording “For the Love of God” he touched on the subject of spirituality. He told us what God means to him, what his relationship with God is, and how that relationship influenced him and his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting subject, that came from a question as well, was about the musical industry, how to protect your intellectual property, how to obtain copyright, why you should do that early in your career, how he did it, and what he learned from Frank Zappa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;jam-session&quot;&gt;Jam Session&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Steve’s talk, the awaited jam session followed. He asked us who would like to participate. I got emotional and shy and hesitated a bit but then I told myself that if I don’t raise my hand now, I would regret forever, so I forced myself and I raised it. We took our guitars and queued near the stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The backing track was a loop from “Building the Church”. Each of us came on to the stage, played a solo for a couple of measures, then Steve played for a couple of measures, and finally both played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before stepping on the stage I had a lot of interesting musical ideas that I would play over the backing track, but when I got there my mind was completely empty and I got a bit scared. In a couple of seconds though, I managed to pull of some interesting phrases, and the duel was good too, we were able to build a small musical relationship. I don’t remember playing a wrong note :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we finished playing, Steve told me “Really good! You should keep on playing!”. After that I tried to see if he said that to any of the other guys after me and I don’t think he did. When I came off the stage I really felt sincere applause. I got praised by Cristi Gram and Nicu Patoi, two of the best guitarists of Romania, I hope they weren’t just polite…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt great, even if I wasn’t able to prove myself like I would have liked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ending&quot;&gt;Ending&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the jam session, the winner of the Ibanez guitar was drawn and the masterclass was over. It felt a bit short, it was announced to be around 3 hours and it only lasted for 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very happy that I had the opportunity to attend and to fulfill a part of my dream. For the fans of autographs I’ll post my JS1200 headstock signature and my Jemini pedal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix mosaicgallery&quot;&gt;
                
    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/Ibanez-Jemini-signed-Steve-Vai.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ibanez Jemini Signed by Steve Vai.&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/Ibanez-Jemini-signed-Steve-Vai.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/Ibanez-Jemini-signed-Steve-Vai.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/Ibanez-Jemini-signed-Steve-Vai.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ibanez Jemini Signed by Steve Vai.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/JS1200-signed-headstock-Steve-Vai.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;JS1200 headstock signed by Steve Vai.&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/JS1200-signed-headstock-Steve-Vai.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/JS1200-signed-headstock-Steve-Vai.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/JS1200-signed-headstock-Steve-Vai.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;JS1200 headstock signed by Steve Vai.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Steve for such a great day, for an unforgettable moment and for words of wisdom that will guide me through life, no matter what.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 04:39:55 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/music/2015/11/01/steve-vai-masterclass.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/music/2015/11/01/steve-vai-masterclass.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>music</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>NUS Lectures</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was in Singapore, I had the great opportunity to teach at NUS. Although I was a research assistant, professor Ye Wang asked me to hold a lecture for his course CS4347: Sound and Music Computing. The idea was to present an introduction to music theory from a musician’s point of view. In other words, how musicians use the elements of music theory in songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding how music theory “works” is essential in order to develop new algorithms that can better analyze songs. For example, if we all agree that the minor scale is used in sad songs and the major scale is used in happy ones, then if we are able to detect it programatically, we will be able to group or search songs by emotions. I touch on this and other interesting aspects in this lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that everybody should teach something that they’re passionate about because they might inspire passion in others. For that matter, I thought that the concept of explaining music theory using feelings would really raise interest and it worked. I received amazing feedback from the students. Here is the full video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IBPrpnK0Sf8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the great feedback received, professor Wang asked me to do another short lecture on introduction to MIDI. Musical Instrument Digital Interface is a protocol that allows musical equipment and computers to talk to each other. This lecture is more on the technical side, but it should be interesting for musicians as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/jT8lXP-H8HA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you like them? Were they engaging? Did they raise your interest? I would really appreciate to hear your comments on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 05:39:55 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>/nus-lectures/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/nus-lectures/</guid>
        
        
        <category>music</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Music Story</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-it-all-started&quot;&gt;How It All Started&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, my father Cornel Cosareanu was one of the most respected guitarists in my hometown. He was in two bands, one called IVO with a blues-rock centered style with club concerts and big stages, and one called Sincron that played at weddings and other events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He took me with him to the rehearsals, and strangely, it didn’t feel boring (imagine that being possible for a 3-4 years old kid). I was somehow fascinated about the cymbals, the shiny metal plates that were moving on the drums. When they took a break I asked to sit at the drums and play, I liked hitting the cymbals with a stick and watch them move. At home, I even used the opened flaps of a cardboard box from a vacuum cleaner as my cymbals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my interest in drums grew, I received my first pair of sticks from one of my father’s drummers, a brown-ish lacquered pair of drumsticks with “Mihai ’95” written on them. After that, I got a large snare drum shell with a paper drum head. It had a horrible sound, nothing similar to a real snare drum. After I obviously broke it from the first hits, my dad applied a good amount of tape, and then I put a blanket on it so that I wouldn’t hear that horrible sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember trying to imitate songs heard on tv like the intro to Cow and Chicken, but the most vivid memory is about the first concert that I’ve ever seen, Guitar Expo ’92 Sevilla, on a VHS tape. That’s how I got to know Joe Satriani, Steve Vai and Brian May. There were many others playing, but this is the music that stayed with me until now (I think I was around 6 when that was happening). I tried to play along with those drummers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5TfcDz5K_NQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing worth mentioning is that when I saw my father practicing the guitar, I didn’t understand at all why a piece of wood with some wires would be so attractive to him, it looked so boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going further, when I was in primary school my father bought a VHS tape with Dave Weckl – Back to Basics, one of my favourite drummers, and I watched it over and over again. Then, after my father was convinced that I want to practice, he made a big financial effort and bought me a set of Romanian drums, green ones, with a jazzy cymbal stand, and two stickers with BMW and Champion on them. There was only one problem, I couldn’t play them in my apartment so I got to use blankets on them (which ripped the fun out of the game).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/old-romanian-drumset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My first set of Romanian drums.&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/old-romanian-drumset.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/old-romanian-drumset.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/old-romanian-drumset.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My first set of Romanian drums.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to take lessons but it didn’t keep me interested, I caught on pretty fast so I got bored and I abandoned them. I moved the drums at my grandmother’s place so that I could play them without blankets. I went there for a couple of weeks during the summer, playing along with music on tape. Until highschool, playing the drums remained a nice hobby for me, I didn’t have whom to share it with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;highschool-of-rockfalling-for-the-drums&quot;&gt;Highschool of Rock/Falling for the Drums&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highschool came, and I got to know a couple of friends interested in music, so in my freshman year we started a band called Desant. The other band members were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vladimir Coman-Popescu – bass guitar &amp;amp; vocals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gabriel Neagu – guitar &amp;amp; vocals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Andrei Jipa – guitar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alin Teodorescu – keyboards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are two pictures of us at our second or third rehearsal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix mosaicgallery&quot;&gt;
                
    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/Desant-band-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Desant band at a rehearsal.&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/Desant-band-2.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/Desant-band-2.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/Desant-band-2.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Desant band at a rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/Desant-band.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Desant band at a rehearsal.&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/Desant-band.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/Desant-band.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/Desant-band.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Desant band at a rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening to our rehearsal recording now I find it funny, but at that time it really seemed an ok quality. We played at the freshman’s prom, and although it wasn’t a great success, it surely wasn’t a fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day after the prom a classmate got a phone call looking for me:&lt;br /&gt;
– “Hey, it’s for you!”&lt;br /&gt;
– “Umm, hello?”&lt;br /&gt;
– “Hi! Are you Mihai Cosareanu?”&lt;br /&gt;
– “Yup, that’s me!”&lt;br /&gt;
– “We were in public at that event and we needed a drummer for a band,
would you like to meet and talk?”&lt;br /&gt;
– “Of course!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I met Iuliana Dobre, one of my dearest friends and a great singer. After she told me her idea, I met Claudiu Cojocaru, the band’s guitarist. The first songs that they emailed me were Roxette – Joyride and Fading Like a Flower, Deep Purple – When a Blind Man Cries and Alannah Myles – Black Velvet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in order to be able to play, we needed some keyboards and a bass player. I knew Alin Teodorescu, one of the greatest keyboard players around, and he joined in right away. We tried probably 4-5 bass players and they all didn’t quite seem a good fit, so we asked another friend of mine, George Statie who was taking guitar lessons at that time to play the bass. Together we formed The Sixteens band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the band got more serious, I had a good reason to convince my parents to stretch a bit and buy me a good drum set. I bought this awesome Pearl Export EX series kit with jet black hardware and double bass drum pedal. It was awesome, a dramatic change in the fun level of playing drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;clearfix mosaicgallery&quot;&gt;
                
    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/pearl-export-ex-jet-black.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First real drum set, Pearl Export EX Series jet black&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/pearl-export-ex-jet-black.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/pearl-export-ex-jet-black.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/pearl-export-ex-jet-black.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First real drum set, Pearl Export EX Series jet black&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/pearl-export-jet-black-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First real drum set, Pearl Export EX Series jet black&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/pearl-export-jet-black-2.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/pearl-export-jet-black-2.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/pearl-export-jet-black-2.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First real drum set, Pearl Export EX Series jet black&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


    

 &lt;div class=&quot;mosaicflow__item&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/images/pearl-export-jet-black-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First real drum set, Pearl Export EX Series jet black&quot; srcset=&quot;            /assets/resized/480/pearl-export-jet-black-3.jpg 480w,            /assets/resized/800/pearl-export-jet-black-3.jpg 800w,            /assets/resized/1200/pearl-export-jet-black-3.jpg 1200w,    &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First real drum set, Pearl Export EX Series jet black&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;meeting-the-six-stringed-piece-of-wood&quot;&gt;Meeting the Six-Stringed Piece of Wood&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was playing drums in The Sixteens, I wanted to be able to play with the band my favourite songs from Joe Satriani or Steve Vai. However, our technique wasn’t good enough to approach this kind of songs and also, the guitarist didn’t resonate with that genre of music so I got motivated to try and see how hard could it be to play those songs on guitar. Until then I picked up the guitar only for a couple of times, I knew just how to play the bassline of Gary Moore – Midnight Blues and the intro to Deep Purple – Smoke on The Water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having no knowledge of notes and harmony at all, I needed to find a way to start. Our bass player, George, showed me the concept of tablature, which is like a musical staff, but instead of notes, the position of your fingers on the guitar neck is notated. Immediately I downloaded the tablature for Always With Me, Always With You and started learning the song. It took me 3 months from zero to memorising the notes, but I was able to play it only at a quarter of the original tempo. In about one year I was able to play it at full speed, but lacking feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I progressed quickly with the guitar, I became impatient with the slow development of our band and the changes in style (we began playing old rock and roll songs which for drums are a little boring) and even with those simple songs we weren’t able to hold a concert for nearly one year. This impatience brought me to quit the band and focus on studying the guitar alone. During highschool I didn’t have too much homework to do (or I didn’t do it anyway :)) so I had a lot of time to practice the guitar. I learned a couple of my favourite songs, I played over backing tracks learning to improvise, I even played live over Yahoo Messenger for a couple of friends that wanted to listen. Being serious about it, my parents got me my first guitar, an Ibanez JS1200 that I absolutely love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;switching-to-guitar&quot;&gt;Switching to Guitar&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I got better and I felt that I could play, a new instrument made it’s way into our house, an Ibanez JS1200. I joined the IVO band as a solo guitarist and my father switched to rhythm guitar. We held our first concert in 2009 in the following formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adrian Rizea – drums&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liviu Briciu – bass guitar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gabriel Ciprian Magda – vocals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cornel Cosareanu – rhythm guitar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011 I participated in a national rock guitar contest for guitarists under 21 organised by Adi Manolovici. I played two songs, Steve Vai – For the Love of God and Joe Satriani – Summer Song and I came on the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013 I held my first solo concert at the Jazz-Rock festival in Campina. The playlist included 13 instrumental rock songs from Steve Vai and Joe Satriani.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;meeting-steve-vai&quot;&gt;Meeting Steve Vai&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great moment of my life that I dreamed of was meeting Steve Vai in person. First time I met him in a press conference before the concert that he held with the Romanian Evolution Tempo Orchestra in Bucharest. I took my guitar and I got an autograph and a nice photo with him. Unfortunately, the autograph was placed where my hand usually sits and it prevented me from playing relaxed, so I decided to wipe it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the moment that I’ve been really waiting for actually happened in June 2013 when he came back and held an Alien Guitar Secrets masterclass. It was a great experience (you can see the link in the bottom of the post for a detailed story). At the end of his talk, he asked who would like to jam with him. It was kinda’ tough to raise my hand, but I forced myself to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got on the stage, I lost every musical idea that I thought of before when I heard that the backing track will be a loop from Building the Church. I was in a pure blank mental state so I had to improvise. There were some of the best musicians from Romania in the audience, but I managed to ignore them and play as if I was alone (admittedly with trembling hands). I managed to bring up some nice musical ideas and that made Steve tell me: “Do not give up!”. He didn’t say that to anybody else, so I felt very privileged. With that event, I also got a better placed autograph on my guitar that still reminds me of that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sound-recording-and-engineering&quot;&gt;Sound Recording and Engineering&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became interested in sound recording and engineering techniques around the time I picked up the guitar. I learned about recording gear in deep technical detail, and read a couple of books on sound, acoustics, recording equipment and techniques. Among the best books I read, I can recommend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Sound Reinforcement Handbook by Gary Davis and Ralph Jones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Audio Expert by Ethan Winer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Recording Engineer’s Handbook by Bobby Owsinski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think ear training is more important than understanding how the gear works, though, and for that matter I have yet to stumble upon something better than Moulton Laboratories Golden Ears series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To practice, I started recording my own drum set with a couple of mics in a small untreated room. I played around with the sound and fooled with EQs, compressors and various effects to understand them better and to develop my ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;composition&quot;&gt;Composition&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering virtual instruments I realised how easy it is to hear your music as being played by a real orchestra or band so I started fooling around with a couple of musical ideas and sketches. Everytime I had a musical idea however, I couldn’t turn it into a song that I would identify myself with, so I ended up having a lot of short sketches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of inspiration doesn’t come to me too often, but when it comes it’s always amazing. It’s like a way of discovering things that you can do, or come up with, that you didn’t even think you are capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still view composition as a kind of magic. I don’t really believe in teaching composition, because I don’t know if anybody truly understands the process. For my music, I really need to feel that every note or rest in a piece of music is there for a reason and has a meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to listen to some of my musical sketches and ideas see the link at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;teaching-music&quot;&gt;Teaching Music&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a nice experience as a research assistant in National University of Singapore. I was part of the Sound and Music Computing lab and professor Ye Wang offered me the great opportunity of holding a lecture in the Sound and Music Computing course where I presented an introduction to music theory. I received great feedback from the students so professor Wang asked me to do another small lecture on introduction to MIDI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these lectures I learned a lot about myself. I think that I really can explain a subject that I truly understand in a way that gets people engaged and interested, without diving into too much detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to watch the lectures, check the link at the bottom of this post and tell me what do you think about the style of teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;now&quot;&gt;Now…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still part of IVO band. Desant is now a nice piece of history. Vladimir started producing electronic music, Gabriel is still engaged in a couple of acoustic and metal musical projects, Andrei moved to the United Kingdom and music is just a hobby for him and Alin is a member of Freestay band. The Sixteens band is now called Xteens and they are actively performing at private parties or in clubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-end&quot;&gt;The End&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really appreciate you for taking your time to read one of the stories of my life. I hope you found it interesting and maybe motivational. Here are the links that I promised above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/music/2015/11/01/steve-vai-masterclass.html&quot;&gt;Steve Vai Masterclass&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nus-lectures/&quot;&gt;NUS Lectures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 05:39:55 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>/my-music-story/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/my-music-story/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>About</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who Am I?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am Mihai Cosareanu and I am &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; an artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-heart-for-feelings&quot;&gt;A Heart for Feelings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love conveying feelings and emotions to people and I do believe that one of the best ways to achieve that is through music. I think it’s a universal language of emotions that we are able to understand even before we are born. No matter how old you are, where you’re from or what language you speak, you are able to feel and enjoy the language of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides playing music, another thing that I spend a lot of time on and that feeds my soul is meeting people and having long emotionally-engaging talks. In fact, I think I have a genuine passion for people. I try to understand every person that I come across, even when our values disagree or when we have different points of view. I found out that this is great for improving your communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-mind-for-thoughts&quot;&gt;A Mind for Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was a child, I haven’t taken things for granted, I have always asked myself questions like “why is this so?” and “how does that work?”. These questions made me look deeper into a lot of subjects such as science, technology, economics, psychology, religion, and philosophy. I have a general curiosity and an endless thirst to understand everything that I come across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that matter, I spend a lot of time thinking. I think about our greatest problems, I think about happiness, the meaning of life, existence and death. I even think about what thinking is, and how it affects my body, my mind and my perceptions. It’s a crazy thought zoo in there :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-story&quot;&gt;My Story&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began to be a part of this world on the 26th of January 1992 in Campina, Romania, a nice and peaceful place, situated around 100 Km from Bucharest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, my father had a rock band and he took me with him to the rehearsals. There I fell in love with the drums, but I didn’t have anyone to share this with until high-school. There I found other guys that could play so we started a band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After one year of actively playing drums, I picked up the guitar and tried to learn my favourite songs from Joe Satriani and Steve Vai. I spent a lot of time practicing guitar, learning notes, harmony and improvising solos over backing tracks and along with that I learned about acoustics, sound engineering and recording techniques. It felt like a true passion, I never got tired of it, I remember one day when I played for about 13 hours with a few breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the economic forecast of becoming a proficient musician scared me at that time so I chose the second thing that I was good at – I pursued a degree in Computer Science at the Politehnica University of Bucharest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a the son of two engineers I had developed a good mind for numbers, but even if I could handle maths, physics and other sciences, I couldn’t think in abstract terms like a real scientist could. I always needed an analogy to a real life situation to be able to understand and relate the concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that time, the path I chose seemed to be a good compromise, though I had to invest a lot of time in my degree and my music development slowed down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I got my degree, I got an opportunity to work as a research assistant at the National University of Singapore’s research lab for Sound and Music Computing. I stayed in Singapore for around 6 months and traveled around in Malaysia Cambodia, and Thailand, then returned back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-am-i-doing-now&quot;&gt;What Am I Doing Now?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I am working as a cloud software engineer at Fitbit. In my free time I play guitar, compose musical pieces, practice sound engineering, take walks, meet people, travel around and feed my curiosity by reading books and taking courses on various subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;get-in-touch-with-me&quot;&gt;Get in Touch with Me&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I could be of value to you or if you just want to get to know me, make sure to drop a message. I am always keen on meeting new people, discovering new ideas, sharing my passion and sharpening my mind :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more detailed story of my music, you can read more &lt;a href=&quot;/my-music-story/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2015 05:39:55 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>/about/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/about/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
